<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Resurrection rescued from the souldiers calumnies, in two sermons preached at St. Maries in Oxon. / By Robert Jones D.D.</title>
            <author>Lushington, Thomas, 1590-1661.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 68 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 55 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88656</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L3503</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1902_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202762</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862945</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862945</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170539</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88656)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170539)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 236:E1902[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Resurrection rescued from the souldiers calumnies, in two sermons preached at St. Maries in Oxon. / By Robert Jones D.D.</title>
                  <author>Lushington, Thomas, 1590-1661.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 100 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Lownds at the White Lion in Pauls Church-yard, neer the little north-door,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Robert Jones = Thomas Lushington. Cf. Wing.</note>
                  <note>The sermons were originally preached in 1624.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Feb:"; The '9' in imprint date is altered to an "8".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Resurrection --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Matthew XXVIII, 13 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Acts II, 1 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170539:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE RESURRECTION Reſcued from the Souldiers Calumnies, In Two <hi>SERMONS</hi> Preached at St. <hi>Maries</hi> in <hi>oxon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY ROBERT JONES D.D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Lownds</hi> at the White <hi>Lion</hi> in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, neer the little North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>door, 1658.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:170539:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170539:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:170539:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170539:3"/>
            <head>The <hi>Stationer</hi> to the <hi>Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T being the conſtant Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom to uſher all ſorts of Books in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the World with a <hi>Preface,</hi> I thought good to give this ſhort
<pb facs="tcp:170539:4"/>Account of the two following <hi>Sermons:</hi> Their Authour Dr. <hi>Robert Jones</hi> (a man ſufficiently emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent for his extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary parts) was appointed to preach a <hi>Reſurrection</hi>-Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon on <hi>Eaſter</hi>-day in St. <hi>Maries</hi> Church in <hi>Oxford;</hi> which be performed with very
<pb facs="tcp:170539:4"/>great applauſe and ſatisfaction. Yet ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving delivered ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the <hi>Repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>-Sermon which did not pleaſe the ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer Palates of ſome of his Auditors, he was oblig'd by the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalls of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſity, to make a <hi>Recantation</hi>-Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon; which how in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geniouſly
<pb facs="tcp:170539:5"/>he perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, I leave the intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent Reader after a ſerious peruſall to judge and cenſure.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Farewell,</hi> R. L.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170539:5"/>
            <head>THE REPETITION SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>MAT. 28.13.</hi>
                  </bibl> 
                  <p>His Diſciples came by night and stole him away while we ſlept.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat's the beſt News abroad? So we muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin: 'Tis the <hi>Garb</hi> (<hi>les novel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les</hi>) the grand ſalute, and common <hi>Preface</hi> to all our
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170539:6"/>talk. And the news goes not as things are in themſelves, but as mensfancies are fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioned, as ſome luſt to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, and others to believe: The ſame relation ſhall goe for true or falſe, according to the key wherein mens minds are tuned; but chiefly as they ſtand diverſe in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, ſo they feign and affect different News. By their <hi>News</hi> ye may know their <hi>Religion,</hi> and by their <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> fore-know their <hi>News.</hi> This week the <hi>Spaniſh Match</hi> goes forward, and <hi>Bethleem Gabors</hi> Troups are broken; and the next week <hi>Bethleem Gabors</hi> Troups goe forward, and the <hi>Spaniſh Match</hi> is bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. The <hi>Catholique</hi> is of the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170539:6"/>
               <hi>Spaniſh match,</hi> and the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant</hi> of reſtoring the <hi>Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinate;</hi> and each party think that the ſafety of the <hi>Church</hi> and ſucceſs of <hi>religion</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon the event of one or other, and therefore they croſs and counter-tell each others news. <hi>Titius</hi> came from <hi>London</hi> yeſterday, and he ſayes that the new Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel at <hi>St. James</hi> is quite fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed: <hi>Caius</hi> came thence but this morning, and then there was no ſuch thing on building. Falſe news follows true at the heels, and often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times outſtrips it.</p>
            <p>Thus goes the <hi>Chronicle</hi>-news, the talke of the <hi>facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> and <hi>pragmatick;</hi> but the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170539:7"/>
               <hi>Chriſtian</hi> news, the talke of the <hi>faithful</hi> is ſpent in <hi>Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelio,</hi> in hearing and telling ſome good news of their <hi>Saviour:</hi> and now all the talk is of his <hi>Reſurrection.</hi> The <hi>Chriſtian</hi> current goes, <hi>News</hi> from <hi>Mount Calvary,</hi> the ſixteenth day of <hi>Niſan,</hi> in the year thirty four, <hi>old ſtyle;</hi> as the three holy Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons deliver it at the <hi>eighth verſe</hi> of this <hi>Chapter.</hi> But ſince there are certain <hi>Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers</hi> arrived, and they ſay there was no ſuch matter as the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> 'twas but a gull put upon the world by his <hi>Diſciples;</hi> for it fares with ſpiritual news as with temporal, it is variouſly and contrarily related, till the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170539:7"/>falſe controls the true. And as our modern <hi>News</hi> comes neither from the <hi>Court</hi> nor the <hi>Camp,</hi> nor from the place where things are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, but is forged in <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticles</hi> by <hi>Prieſts,</hi> or in ſome <hi>Pauls Aſſembly,</hi> or ſuch like place; and the divulge committed to ſome vigilant and watchful tongue: So it is with the <hi>News</hi> of the <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſurrection;</hi> it came not from <hi>Mount Calvary,</hi> but the <hi>Prieſts</hi> are the <hi>Authors</hi> of it, at the <hi>eleventh</hi> verſe; and at the <hi>twelveth,</hi> they frame and mould it to the mouth of the <hi>Watch.</hi> The <hi>Divul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,</hi> men of double credit, they <hi>know</hi> the truth, for they are of the <hi>Watch,</hi> and they
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170539:8"/>will not <hi>lye,</hi> for they are <hi>Souldiers;</hi> nay, they will maintain it, for they are <hi>Knights, Milites, Knights of the Poſt,</hi> they are hired to ſay, ſaying, and they did ſay, <hi>His Diſciples came by night and ſtole him away whilſt we ſlept.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The words ſo plain, they need no opening. May it pleaſe you that I make <hi>three Curſories</hi> over them; One for the <hi>Souldiers,</hi> another for the <hi>Diſciples,</hi> and the third for our <hi>Saviour.</hi> In the two former we will beat the point <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con,</hi> and in the latter reconcile it, for that's the faſhion alſo. No <hi>error</hi> ſo abſurd but finds a <hi>Patron,</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:170539:8"/>nor <hi>Truth</hi> ſo ſound but meets with an <hi>Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> nor point controverted but the oppoſite tenent may be reconciled; be they di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant as <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Hell,</hi> as incompatible as <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> yet they ſhall meet with a <hi>Moderator,</hi> and a <hi>cogging diſtinction</hi> ſhall ſtate the queſtion on the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurder ſide. Firſt then for the <hi>Souldiers,</hi> whoſe <hi>Curſory</hi> hath no parts, that's not the <hi>Souldiers</hi> manner, but yet is ſprinkled with <hi>abſurdities,</hi> that's the manner of the <hi>Watch.</hi> They ſpeak partly as they fight, <hi>voluntarily,</hi> and partly as they watch, <hi>ſupinely.</hi> And thus they begin their talk:</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:170539:9"/>
            <p>Ye men and people of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> This <hi>Jeſus of Nazareth</hi> was a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Jugler,</hi> a neat Compiler of <hi>Impostures,</hi> pretended title to the crown of <hi>Judah,</hi> made himſelf the <hi>Meſsias</hi> and the Son of <hi>God,</hi> brought ſuch ſtrange opinions as would turn the whole world out of <hi>bias;</hi> having no proof from ſenſe or reaſon for his <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velties,</hi> he would needs confirm them by <hi>miracles;</hi> and in the worlds eye he ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to do <hi>wonders,</hi> though his works were indeed but meer deluſions, wrought by ſlight of hand, <hi>hocus pocus.</hi> All which was ſo manifeſtly diſcovered, that to ſtop the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170539:9"/>current of ſuch falſe coin, my <hi>Lord Preſident</hi> was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to nail him to the <hi>Croſſe</hi> for a <hi>Counterfeit.</hi> His <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-trick</hi> was that of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection,</hi> whereof he fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpake in his life-time: for he was no ordinary dealer, but would make his Cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to ſurvive his perſon, and durſt fore-ſay ſo. To put this piece in Execution, he entertained a rabble of <hi>Ruffians,</hi> whom he termed his <hi>Diſciples,</hi> as all <hi>Plotters</hi> have <hi>Partners:</hi> Theſe he inſtructed in the game while he lived, and they were to play it when he was dead. The liſt of his <hi>Diſciples</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted of <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Women;</hi> for in all crafty carriages
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170539:10"/>there lyes a <hi>Womans</hi> part. The <hi>men</hi> were to perform all manner of <hi>fact,</hi> and the <hi>women,</hi> whoſe activity lies in their tongue, were to report the <hi>miracle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>High-prieſts</hi> and ſome of the <hi>Sanedrim</hi> being wiſe to apprehend, and wary to prevent the dangerous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences hereof, procured a warrant from the <hi>Preſident</hi> to ſeal up the <hi>Tomb,</hi> and place a <hi>Watch</hi> there; and we were the parties appointed to guard it. The Charge we underwent required good ſervice, for his <hi>Diſciples</hi> were common <hi>Night-wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> like their Maſter, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table <hi>Cutters,</hi> and carried as
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170539:10"/>much courage as cunning; ſuch tall fellows with their weapons, that they made it but a ſleight either to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand or aſſault a whole mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, and durſt do any thing in their Maſters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half. The other night, when we apprehended him in <hi>Gethſemane,</hi> we were moſt of the luſtieſt fellows in <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> and pretty well ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, yet they ſtood to it ſtoutly, made a tall fray, and ſometimes put us to the worſt: At the firſt <hi>On-ſet</hi> we were all knock'd down, and at our <hi>Recovery, Rabbi Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus,</hi> a follower of the <hi>High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieſts</hi> company and our Captain, was ſingled out by one of their ſide, a <hi>Sayler</hi> he
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170539:11"/>ſeemed, who with his whin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard lopt off one of his ears, and had the blow light right, it would have cleft him down to the twiſt. Nay they were all <hi>Bravers,</hi> and their bloody mind was ſeen upon <hi>Judas Iſcariot,</hi> one of their own company, who becauſe he was our Blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hound to ſent their Maſter out, they perſecuted the poor wretch till they had paunch'd him; for not far from their walk he was found hang'd with his guts about his heels. And for their bloody pranks that way, the place begins to bear the name of <hi>Aceldama,</hi> the bloody field.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:170539:11"/>
            <p>For the exploit of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, they had the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of their fellow-<hi>ſhe-diſciples,</hi> night houſe-wives too, for they were hovering about the <hi>Sepulchre</hi> from the dead of the night till the morning, and were as the <hi>Counter-watch</hi> to give notice of ſome advantage to the <hi>Diſciples,</hi> who lay not far off, ſome where above ground, while their maſter was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it. All the day-time they ſtir not for fear of <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers,</hi> frequenting to and fro in the gardens and walks about <hi>Mount Calvary;</hi> it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing both <hi>Sabbath</hi> and <hi>Paſſeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver;</hi> but in the night they took their opportunity by this means: We had been
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170539:12"/>extreamly over-travell'd, both to apprehend and guard him, firſt, to the <hi>High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieſt,</hi> next to the <hi>Preſident;</hi> from him to <hi>Herod,</hi> and back again; then to his <hi>arraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> then to his <hi>Execution</hi> and ever ſince at his <hi>grave;</hi> ſo turbulent the man was, that his very dead body would not lye ſtill and be quiet. This <hi>over-watching,</hi> ſeconded with the darkneſs of the <hi>night,</hi> and <hi>coldneſſe</hi> of the <hi>ayre,</hi> caſt us into a heavy <hi>ſleep;</hi> thereupon the <hi>women</hi> give the <hi>watch-word</hi> to the <hi>Diſciples,</hi> who immediately do <hi>exhumate</hi> his body; and while they tranſlate and bury it elſewhere, the <hi>wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> trot into the <hi>Town,</hi> and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170539:12"/>bruit it abroad that their <hi>Maſter</hi> is riſen.</p>
            <p>And the credulous City is partly inclined to believe the <hi>Legerdemain;</hi> they are willing to frame their faith and build their ſalvation up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a flying gull, raiſed by three <hi>way-going</hi> women, <hi>gadling Goſsips</hi> that came from <hi>Galilee; One</hi> of them <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious,</hi> ſo divelliſh that there came <hi>ſeven</hi> divells out of her, how many ſtaid behind <hi>God</hi> knows; it is like ſhe was ſo full, there was room for no more; and by her ye may gueſs at her compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Conſider of it; the matter is of moment, a main point of State, that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170539:13"/>concerns your own Nation: We are but ſtrangers, and no farther intereſſed then for the truths ſake to ſpeak it; and therefore be adviſed whether ye will rely herein upon the word of a <hi>woman,</hi> or upon the faith and repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of a <hi>Souldier.</hi> And here the <hi>Souldier</hi> puts up, he ſheaths his malicious and blaſphemous tongue, more ſharp and deadly then his ſword, and gives our <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our</hi> a wound more mortal far then thoſe upon the Croſs; they did but put him in a trance, ſuſpend his life for a day or two, at the moſt but kill his <hi>Humanity;</hi> but this would murther his <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity,</hi> and dead his <hi>Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality,</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:170539:13"/>it would nullifie the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and fruſtrate all our <hi>Faith:</hi> for, <hi>If Chriſt be not riſen</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>then is our preaching vain, and your faith is alſo vain.</hi> And therefore I come to my ſecond <hi>Curſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, For his Diſciples ſtole him away by night.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Herein we will deal <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianly</hi> and civilly, not give the lye to the <hi>Souldiers,</hi> foul words to the <hi>Watch:</hi> But yet we may ſay, that their tale hath no truth in any point of it, but a meer ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Saying,</hi> ſay ye. They ſay not of themſelves, but as the <hi>Priests</hi> taught them; they knew they ſaid falſe, and therefore our ſaying to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170539:14"/>the contrary will eaſily ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain. And therein we fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low not the <hi>Random</hi> of their roving, but take the ſum of their ſaying, as it is here ſet down by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it order and parts. The words then may eaſily be taken <hi>Judiciarily,</hi> in form of an accuſation, and then <hi>Morally</hi> they are <hi>Calumny;</hi> the <hi>Souldiers</hi> either not heard, or not practiſed the doctrine of <hi>John Baptiſt, Accuſe no man falſely.</hi> Or they may be taken popular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in form of a report or ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, and then morally they are a meer <hi>gull</hi> or <hi>ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</hi> In what ſenſe ſoever, there are three parties wron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in them; The <hi>Diſciples,</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:170539:14"/>our <hi>Saviour,</hi> and the <hi>Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> themſelves. The <hi>Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> here are tax'd of <hi>theft,</hi> that they - ſhould come by night, and ſteal away their <hi>Maſter:</hi> Our <hi>Saviour</hi> of <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potency</hi> and <hi>Impoſture,</hi> that he neither could nor did riſe from the dead, but was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed away by his <hi>Diſciples:</hi> And the <hi>Souldiers</hi> of capital negligence, that they were aſleep. In the <hi>Curſory</hi> then for the <hi>Diſciples,</hi> may ye pleaſe that I lay down three plain <hi>Contradictories</hi> ro the words of the <hi>Text,</hi> as they lie in order: Firſt, <hi>the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples came not hither by night.</hi> Secondy, <hi>he was not ſtole a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>the Souldiers were not aſleep.</hi> For proof
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170539:15"/>of each whereof there are no cogent demonſtrations in nature <hi>Quòd ſint;</hi> ſingle vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary actions that leave no evident effect, admit it not. We preach not before <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Infidels,</hi> to whom this doctrine is ſcandalous and fool ſhneſs; but the ſimple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted <hi>Christian,</hi> the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling hearer ſhall have ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall probabilities, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſive arguments, ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to convey belief into a heart illuminated, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared by grace for it. For the firſt then, <hi>His Diſciples came not by night.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The body moves not vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily, unleſs the motion be grounded upon the Will;
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170539:15"/>ſo that when the influence of the Will upon the exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal members is either inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted or fruſtrated by any forreign accident, the body hardly admits of going and comming. The heart, and firſt mover of the <hi>Diſciples,</hi> was now mated and ſet up by a Leaſe of impetuous paſſions. All thoſe <hi>Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents</hi> of the Soul which have miſchiefs for their <hi>Objects,</hi> and are immediately diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to the <hi>Patient</hi> that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dures them, as <hi>ſorrow, fear</hi> and <hi>deſpair,</hi> did now wholly poſſeſs them: Extreme ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for their <hi>Maſters</hi> preſent <hi>ſufferings,</hi> as much <hi>fear</hi> for their own future <hi>danger,</hi> and their like <hi>deſpaire</hi> for their
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170539:16"/>fore hoped <hi>happineſſe.</hi> Their ſenſes ſeel the <hi>ſorrow,</hi> their <hi>fear</hi> torments their fancies, and their memory maintains their <hi>deſpair;</hi> their whole ſoul ſo aſſaulted, that there wanted nothing but a Fever to make them quite fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick. And <hi>Peter</hi> came neer to that, ſo diſtracted, that for his <hi>Masters</hi> ſake firſt he will needs <hi>fight,</hi> then he <hi>flyes away;</hi> anon again he <hi>follows</hi> after him, at length he <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwears</hi> him, and in the end <hi>goes out</hi> and <hi>cries.</hi> In this mode he is carried up and down, till he layes a clog on his conſcience, that would hold him work enough without coming to <hi>Mount Calvary.</hi> The caſe of his
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170539:16"/>other fellows might be as bad, or worſe, although the <hi>Scripture</hi> be therein ſilent. Thus far they go all with <hi>Peter,</hi> that they <hi>ſleep,</hi> and <hi>flye,</hi> and <hi>follow after off.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But when their <hi>Maſter</hi> was paſt all recovery, then each paſſion plaid his part to hinder all humour from comming to <hi>Mount Calvary.</hi> Their ſorrow contracts, and cloſeth them up in <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem: Sorrow</hi> loves to be pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate and lurk in a corner. <hi>Fear</hi> kept them within doors: <hi>Fear</hi> dare not go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, eſpecially in the night, if ſhe do, it is to flie a danger, not to invite it. And to <hi>Deſpair</hi> all buſineſs muſt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170539:17"/>yield: deſpair will not ſtir in her own behalf, unleſs to do her ſelf a miſchief, but of any other ſhe is quite careleſs. To ſay then they came by night, makes it but the more unlikely. They could not watch one hour with him in <hi>Gethſemane</hi> when it concerned his life, while there was yet hope to vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate him from the Croſs; and can they now watch with him a whole night when he was dead and buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? If they were for a nights exploit, they would have done it the night before, when there was a fairer op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portuuity, and greater ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. They now had no more means this night, but
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170539:17"/>more danger. When they they went to <hi>Gethſemane,</hi> they had but two Swords in all, and were there diſarmed of them; but one coat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peece, and ſome ſtript of that; no weapon to aſſault, nor armour to defend. Fit furniture, and fair voyage for poor <hi>Fiſhermen</hi> to make to <hi>Mount Calvary</hi> in a dark night, to affront the <hi>Roman</hi> Watch. And to what end? if their Maſter could riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, what need they come hither? if not, they did him no wrong to abandon him.</p>
            <p>But why mention we the <hi>Reſurrection?</hi> they came not thither, not to a thought of it. He had indeed fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170539:18"/>them of it, but they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood it not: they could not proſecute what they never apprehended; could they hope to make others believe what they could not imagine? Could others grant that feareable, which they eſteemed impoſſible? or had they once belief, yet they forſook it when they forſook their <hi>Maſter.</hi> They were beaten from it in <hi>Geth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemane,</hi> where but one of the <hi>Jews</hi> received any loſſe, and he but of one of his <hi>eares,</hi> and that reſtored again; but they all loſt every one his faith, they loſt their <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our,</hi> and their <hi>Souls</hi> to boot. They were now as faithleſs as their fellow <hi>Judas,</hi> as
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170539:18"/>faithleſs in their Maſter as he was to him. The Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection quite forgot, not onely the thing it ſelf, but their Maſters mention of it: and therefore they embalm his dead body, and do en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tombe it as forlorn. The <hi>Priests</hi> themſelves believed more then the <hi>Diſciples:</hi> they feared it, and therefore fortified the <hi>Sepulcher;</hi> but the <hi>Diſciples</hi> did not ſo much as hope. And when he was riſen <hi>de facto,</hi> they could not believe it, though the women avouched it: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the womens talk ſeemes an old Wives tale, when they tell the <hi>Diſciples</hi> of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection. <hi>Thomas</hi> will not
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170539:19"/>truſt his own eyes though he ſee, and his eares though he hear him. Had they any by-intent, they would have been very forward to report and ſpread the fame; but they ſtood mute at it, and began to ſpread themſelves each man what way his fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy led him: the fame of the Reſurrection did not fright them. And how came the newes abroad? who told it to the high <hi>Prieſts?</hi> not his <hi>Diſciples,</hi> nor the women, but the <hi>Souldiers</hi> here them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. But why ſtand we to defend <hi>the Diſciples</hi> in a fact never committed? no ſuch thing done as they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected. He was not ſtole a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170539:19"/>at all; <hi>My ſecond Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictorie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor by the <hi>Diſciples,</hi> nor by any elſe, unleſs men were mad, or weary of their lives. The advantage of the <hi>Act</hi> could no way recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence the <hi>danger.</hi> The <hi>Lawes</hi> ſo ſtrict for medling with <hi>Sepulchers,</hi> that they could expect no leſſe then to incur the crime of <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge;</hi> which may be ſeen at large in the Digeſts <hi>de Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chro violato:</hi> which Lawes, though ſince compiled, yet for the moſt part were then and there in force, the <hi>Jews</hi> being under the <hi>Roman Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction.</hi> And though they ſhould plead that they did
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170539:20"/>onely tranſlate the body, not abuſe it, yet they could not avoid the <hi>Objection</hi> of <hi>dolus malus,</hi> and ſo incur an arbitrary cenſure, which would be layd very heavily upon them, things running as they did againſt our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour.</hi> What fair <hi>Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> could they look for on his behalf, when he himſelf was charged with <hi>Treaſon,</hi> for asking a peny to pay tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute? Or if ſome had the will to ſteal him, yet none had the power or meanes to perform it. The <hi>Watch</hi> there, termed Souldiers, were of a middle nature between <hi>Souldiers</hi> and <hi>Hangmen; Spiculatores,</hi> they carried a ſpeare in their hands, but a
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170539:20"/>halter at their girdles, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ready for any deadly ſervice. They were <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Satellites,</hi> a Guard to the <hi>Governour;</hi> and <hi>Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, Jaylours, Warders</hi> for <hi>Priſoners;</hi> and <hi>Vigiles, Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> for their bodies who ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered: the common <hi>Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioners</hi> of corporal puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whether it reached onely to ſenſe, or forward to life. To expreſs their <hi>Roman</hi> nature home, the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Nation borrowed Language from the <hi>Weſtern,</hi> the <hi>Greeks</hi> from the <hi>Latine, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtodia;</hi> and the <hi>Syriaque,</hi> as Maſter <hi>Fuller</hi> obſerves, from <hi>Quaeſtionarij, Officers ad quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionem &amp; inquiſitionem, Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioners</hi> or <hi>Inquiſitors, Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentors,</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:170539:21"/>or <hi>Serjeants of the Rack,</hi> to extort <hi>Confeſsions</hi> in criminal <hi>Examinations.</hi> At the peril of their life it was, if the party under their <hi>exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution</hi> did not endure the <hi>extremity</hi> of the <hi>Law.</hi> If the <hi>Priſoner</hi> eſcaped with no puniſhment, or with leſſe, or <hi>in ultimo ſupplicio</hi> recovered by his life, or his dead body otherwiſe diſpoſed then the <hi>Lawes</hi> ordained or permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, then were thoſe <hi>Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers</hi> to take the room of the <hi>Priſoners,</hi> to be waſted and ſpent out upon the ſame puniſhment whereto the <hi>Priſoner</hi> was liable; <hi>Ejuſmodi paena conſumendi,</hi> the very words of the <hi>Law.</hi> Could any man now imagine the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170539:21"/>
               <hi>Watch</hi> could now be either ſo careleſs, or ſuch Cowards as to let our <hi>Saviour</hi> to be ſtole away? Men durſt as well have fetcht him from the <hi>Croſſe</hi> as from the <hi>Grave.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſay that they were ſuch maimed <hi>Souldiers,</hi> as that they had neither eye to <hi>watch,</hi> nor heart to ward; yet the <hi>Sepulcher</hi> it ſelf was ſo impregnable, that it alone would ſecure the body. There could be no burglary, nor breaking it up, no un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermining; The <hi>Soyl</hi> was <hi>Pick-axe</hi> proof, a firm Rock ſpred out of the Roots of <hi>Golgotha,</hi> gabion'd and rough-caſt with flint. No
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170539:22"/>removing of the <hi>Tombe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone;</hi> that beſides its weight &amp; ſullennes to give way, was rib'd and claſped down with Iron barres and bonds; the cloſure ſouldered with the Seal of the <hi>Sanedrim.</hi> Their <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, their fortifying the <hi>Sepulcher,</hi> and ſealing up the Stone, ſayes it was ſo, in the latter verſe of the former Chapter. For though he ſhould revive, yet the high <hi>Prieſts</hi> never meant he ſhould riſe more, either by his own, or by the ſtrength of others. The <hi>Watch</hi> was but a ſtale to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour their pretence, and to lead their requeſt to <hi>Pilate.</hi> The Womens, <hi>Who ſhall roll
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170539:22"/>us away the Stone?</hi> was a matter more then they ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined, a task above the ſtrength of a man. A whole ſet of leavers could not lift it: no rolling it away but by the force of an <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now look into the <hi>Grave,</hi> ſee the remains of the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partiall witneſſes and ſilent ſayings that he was not ſtole away. The <hi>Linnen</hi> and <hi>Grave-Clothes</hi> wherein he was involved, lined and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with a compound of <hi>Myrrhe, Aloes</hi> and <hi>Maſtick,</hi> gums and ſpices <hi>Arabique,</hi> unguents and balms of <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lead,</hi> a Seare-cloth both
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170539:23"/>coſtly and maſſie, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to the worth or weight of an hundred pounds, ſomewhat unwieldy to be handled: the <hi>Kerchief</hi> ſo wrapt and diſpleited, as though yet it had not been uſed; and yet ſo laid aſide, as though he would have come again. What man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of men would leave theſe things thus? His friends would not for ſhame have ſtript him, and carried him away naked. His ſoes would have eſteemed the <hi>Linnen</hi> and embalming <hi>Compounds</hi> farre beyond his <hi>body. Friend</hi> or <hi>Foe,</hi> or <hi>Newter,</hi> they durſt not ſtay to flea the glewy <hi>Seare-cloth</hi> from his skin, and give a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170539:23"/>folding to the <hi>Ker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief.</hi> But if notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding he was ſtolne away, why was not ſearch made to recover his body? no <hi>Hue and Cry</hi> to purſue the <hi>Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors?</hi> no <hi>Proclamation</hi> out for their attachment? why were not the <hi>Women</hi> apprehended, or taken up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuſpicion? why not ſo much as queſtioned? Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned! about what? The <hi>Souldiers</hi> knew well enough he was not ſtolne away; for they ſate by, and markt it; they were the <hi>Watch,</hi> and they did <hi>watch,</hi> they were not aſleep; which is my laſt Contradictory.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:170539:24"/>
            <p>Hitherto they talk like <hi>ſouldiers,</hi> of coming by night, and ſtealing away; now like <hi>Watchmen,</hi> in ſaying they were aſleep. So ſottiſh and unreaſonable is malice, that to burn his neighbours houſe, he will ſet fire on his own; to bring in an accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> they make confeſſion of a crime in themſelves: they gull and befool them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and ſay that the <hi>Watch</hi> was aſleep. It may be as <hi>Watchmen</hi> they durſt ſleep, tis ordinary; but they durſt not ſo as <hi>Souldiers,</hi> their diſcipline too ſtrict, and the penalty thereof too ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere. He that forſakes the <hi>watch, capite punitur,</hi> tis death
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170539:24"/>(ſaith <hi>Paulus</hi>) in law 9. <hi>in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubias, §. de re militari;</hi> and ſome good captains interpret ſleep equivalent to abſence; what ever were the Letter of the Law, practice made it ſo. And <hi>Polybius</hi> tells us it was ſo put in <hi>excution.</hi> If any man of the <hi>Watch</hi> be found aſleep, (ſaith he) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, he is put to the <hi>Bastinado,</hi> a <hi>capital</hi> puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and reach'd to the head: For the then <hi>Baſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do</hi> was <hi>Fuſte caeditur;</hi> and as they now paſſe the Pikes, a thouſand to one but the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty died under it. A whole <hi>Squadron</hi> of men being to do execution, one back-friend or other would paſh out his brains, as now one
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170539:25"/>pike or other would broch him through. The <hi>Roman</hi> Diſcipline extreme dogged, and ſo profeſt it ſelf, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally toward the <hi>Watch.</hi> The <hi>Ban-doggs</hi> of the <hi>Capitol,</hi> becauſe they barked not that night when the <hi>Gaules</hi> ſurprized it, had their leggs broken, and were ſplit alive upon a two-forkt ſtake ſet up in publick; and in memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thereof (ſaith <hi>Livie</hi>) ſome doggs were yearly ſo uſed, for examples ſake to make <hi>Watch-men</hi> beware.</p>
            <p>And the <hi>Rounders</hi> ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial herein, that they would make execution <hi>ipſo facto. Epaminondas</hi> walks the <hi>Round,</hi> and finding one
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170539:25"/>
               <hi>ſouldier</hi> aſleep, ſome of the <hi>Corrounders</hi> entreat for him; well, ſaith he, for your ſakes I will leave him as I found him, and therewithall he ſtakes him to the ground with his <hi>Halbert:</hi> he found him in a dead ſleep, and ſo he left him. Some dimme prints of that <hi>Diſcipline</hi> are ſeen to this day in our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern warrs, where ſometime the <hi>Rounder</hi> will clap a <hi>muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket-ſhot</hi> through a ſleepy head. But anciently they durſt do no other; for to wink at the fault, or delay the puniſhment, was in the Governour <hi>Patrimonii &amp; aeſtimationis damnum,</hi> a loſſe of lands and honour; and in under-Officers <hi>capitale
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170539:26"/>ſupplicium.</hi> They durſt not then ſleep wilfully, and they had no need to ſleep, they were not over-watcht. How the <hi>Day-watch</hi> ſtood I have not yet read; but for the <hi>Night-watch,</hi> all the World knows it was divided into four equal parts, each con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining three Planetary houres, or one quarter of the night, how long or ſhort ſoever. And the turn came about but every third night, and then every third hour they were relieved by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in a freſh <hi>Watch.</hi> It was now paſt the <hi>Vernal Aequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctial,</hi> no <hi>one Night-watch</hi> ſate full three modern houres; ſo three houres over in above threeſcore would
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170539:26"/>bring no <hi>over-watching.</hi> See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then they neither durſt nor did, why yet do they ſay they were aſleep? The reaſon is, they are of the ragged <hi>Regiment,</hi> mercena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Souldiers,</hi> hired to it by the <hi>Prieſts</hi> with a large piece of money. The <hi>Provant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> will undertake to ſay any thing, yea, to do any thing for money; for ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groats a Week tug at a Wheel-barrow, and fo a ſtiver more ſerve the <hi>enemy,</hi> and for a Peece piſtol a <hi>Prince;</hi> ſuffer any thing for money, for a <hi>Dollar</hi> take the <hi>Strappado;</hi> for a brace, draw at a <hi>decimation.</hi> Thus the <hi>Prieſts</hi> dealt with the ſilly <hi>Souldiers,</hi> as they did with
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170539:27"/>
               <hi>Judas,</hi> onely put them upon hanging. An old trick of the <hi>Priests,</hi> and much in uſe at this day, ſaving that now they practiſe it one upon the other, and ſo let them; good ſpeed may they have.</p>
            <p>But for all this they might be aſleep, whether our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour</hi> were ſtole away or no. Somewhat the begging <hi>Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers</hi> would have, &amp; they ſhal, his ſtealing away we can by nomeans grant. The <hi>Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> an article of our <hi>Creed,</hi> the very <hi>groundſel</hi> of all our Faith: his <hi>Reſurrection</hi> the pattern &amp; pledge of ours, the tenure where by we hold our title to <hi>ſalvation.</hi> But for their being aſleep we wil not much contend; it is credible
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:170539:27"/>they were ſo, the contrary being neither implied, nor expreſſed in the <hi>Scripture.</hi> But yet their ſleep is no proof of their ſaying. They know the things were done juſt as they ſay, for they were aſleep the while. A right <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> reaſon, a proof put from a <hi>Prieſt</hi> to ſerve a ſleepy <hi>Souldier.</hi> If they were aſleep, how could they ſay he was ſtollen rather then riſen? or if they ſuppoſe him ſtollen, how knew they his <hi>Diſciples</hi> did it rather then other men? This muſt needs argue in them either calumny to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe a party without cauſe, or levity to lay the cauſe upon a wrong party; either way folly to alledg ſo ſenſeles areaſon.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170539:28"/>All our knowledge is either from Senſe, or Reaſon; from Reaſon they could not have it, that hath made againſt them all this while; from any ſenſe they could not, for they were aſleep, in ſleep all ſenſation is intercepted. They could neither hear, ſee, ſmell, taſte nor feel the <hi>Diſciples</hi> coming, or his ſtealing; if they did, they were not aſleep. If ſome one were awake, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it, why did he not give an <hi>Alarum</hi> to the reſt? if they underſtood it after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards from others, why do they not produce authentick witneſſes? If the <hi>Diſciples</hi> themſelves confeſſed it, why were they not puniſhed,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170539:28"/>and order taken to ſtop the rumour of the <hi>Reſurrection?</hi> There is no way now left, but to pretend the <hi>Spirit,</hi> as our <hi>Enthuſiaſts</hi> do, and to ſay, that while they ſlept they had it in a dream by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation. But that is refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by retortion of the ſame, for by revelation eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Christian</hi> knowes the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary;</hi> God reveals it unto him.</p>
            <p>But why do the <hi>Souldiers</hi> produce this reaſon? the reaſon is, they took it upon truſt from the <hi>Prieſts.</hi> It is an old errour (let us not contend for the age) to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that the <hi>Prieſt</hi> cannot erre. But why are the <hi>Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers</hi>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:170539:29"/>got thus to argue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt themſelves? the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, no body elſe durſt do it. In thoſe times the <hi>ſouldiers</hi> bare all the ſway, aſſumed all power to make <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Emperours.</hi> But ſince the <hi>Prieſt</hi> hath done the like, putting the <hi>Souldier</hi> by. And now the <hi>Peaſant</hi> thinks tis come to his turn, under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of his priviledge in <hi>Parliament:</hi> he would diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths,</hi> and rather then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn it to the <hi>Prieſt</hi> from whom he hath taken it, would caſt the courſe back again upon the <hi>Souldiers.</hi> Nothing now contents the <hi>Commonalty</hi> but <hi>Warre</hi> and <hi>Contention;</hi> he hath taken a
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170539:29"/>ſurfeit of <hi>peace,</hi> the very name of it growes odious: Now to give the <hi>Souldier</hi> his Paſport, we ſumme up four exceptions againſt his ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; Firſt, it is not <hi>veriſimile,</hi> the unlikelihood of it hath appeared in every <hi>Contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory.</hi> Secondly, They were <hi>ignari rerum,</hi> had no infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of what they affirm; neither eye, nor ear-witneſs of what they ſay, for they confeſs themſelves aſleep. Thirdly, Their ſaying is contrary to what they had ſaid before; in the morning they told another tale, at the eleventh verſe of this Chapter; if that were true, this is falſe; if that were not true, why ſhould we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170539:30"/>this? or who will truſt men in contrary tales? Laſtly, the parties were corrupted, hired with a large ſumme to utter their ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, at the twelfth verſe. Theſe two latter lie without the Text, and therefore I wholly forbear them, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for the point of <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption:</hi> 'Tis a crafty crime, and commonly hard to prove. We alſo forbear the lie to the <hi>Souldier,</hi> becauſe he abhorres it. But to the <hi>Prieſts</hi> who put this lie in their mouths, and to their <hi>Diſciple-Prieſts</hi> who at this day practiſe lying, and allow it to be lawful, we would mend the old ſaying, <hi>A Liar ſhould have a good
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170539:30"/>memory,</hi> and rather require in him a good Wit. His memory ſerves but to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void <hi>contradictions</hi> of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but his Wit to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the <hi>contradictions</hi> of others, that an untruth ſeem not alſo unlikely. If therefore the <hi>Prieſts</hi> would have lied wiſely, and with credit, like <hi>Satan</hi> himſelf, the <hi>Serpent</hi> whom they ſerved, they ſhould, as they did for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, have laid our <hi>Saviour</hi> to <hi>Satan</hi>'s charge, and have ſaid, that the foul <hi>Fiend</hi> came by night &amp; fetcht him away; leaving out, <hi>whil'ſt the watch ſlept,</hi> and inſtead there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of have argued from the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent of the Angel, and the earthquake: this could not ſo
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170539:31"/>eaſily have been diſcovered; but it might even as eaſily, where <hi>Faith</hi> had a <hi>Fortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; Humane reaſons</hi> urged againſt it are but as <hi>Paper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhot.</hi> Carnal wiſdom work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt <hi>God</hi> is but dirt and rottenneſs. Our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels are confounded, when carried againſt <hi>Chriſt.</hi> And ſo I come to my third and laſt Curſory, upon the word of our <hi>Saviour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hitherto we have cleared the <hi>Diſciples,</hi> but we muſt alſo give the <hi>Souldier</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. There is no ſuch difference, but the matter may be reconciled, and the queſtion ſtated on the <hi>Souldiers</hi> ſide. Said I not,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:170539:31"/>it was the faſhion? The <hi>Souldiers</hi> then are in the right, their ſaying very ſound and <hi>Chriſtian;</hi> A <hi>Diſciple</hi> of his did come by night, and ſtole him away, and the <hi>Souldiers</hi> were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep. A <hi>Diſciple</hi> of his, and his moſt beloved <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple,</hi> his humane ſoul came by night, was united to his body, raiſed it, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew it from the <hi>Sepulcher</hi> by ſtealth, while the <hi>Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers</hi> were ſo between ſleeping and waking that they perceived it not. Of this <hi>Curſory</hi> very briefly, as the words lie in order, declining all emergent <hi>Controverſies,</hi> for that our
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170539:32"/>preſent quarrel lay onely with the <hi>Souldier.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We term him a Diſciple, who receives knowledge and chaſtiſement from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother. As our <hi>Saviour</hi> was <hi>God,</hi> his <hi>ſoul</hi> was: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the trueſt and moſt proper Diſciple that ever was: it had received both knowledge and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſement, as never man had, knowledge of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, both Divine and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, infuſed and acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: but whether it had no <hi>Ignorance,</hi> we leave it to the <hi>Catholicks.</hi> And all manner of chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, both exemplary, and ſatisfactory, for all
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170539:32"/>
               <hi>Mankind;</hi> the chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our peace was upon it: but whether it ſatisfied for <hi>Reprobates,</hi> we leave it to the <hi>Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians.</hi> His ſoul came, it could move, for it was ſeparate; the ſoul was from the body, though neither from the <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head:</hi> as all the reſt of the Diſciples, it forſook him on the <hi>Croſſe,</hi> and now it came again: but it came not as it went, it went by violence and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign force, the <hi>Jewes</hi> expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led it from him, although he alſo willing it ſhould go; but it came purely volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, by a domeſtick agent: but whether by vertue of the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170539:33"/>
               <hi>Godhead,</hi> or its own mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive faculty, we leave to the <hi>School-men.</hi> It came then, not as poor <hi>Lazarus</hi> ſoul came to <hi>Abraham</hi>'s boſom, carried by <hi>Angels,</hi> but ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle upon its own force, and without any help of others: But whether attended and waited upon by a troop of Angels, we leave it to the <hi>Fathers. For the time,</hi> it came by <hi>Night,</hi> not for fear of the <hi>Jews,</hi> as <hi>Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demus</hi> came to him, but for love of his promiſe, that he might riſe the <hi>third day.</hi> He came the <hi>ſecond</hi> Night, the Night <hi>ſecond</hi> to his <hi>Paſsion,</hi> but third to the day of his <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection,</hi> ſome time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170539:33"/>Mid-night and Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; but at what time, we leave it to the <hi>Chronolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</hi> The <hi>Undè</hi> of its coming was from ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where elſe, from a diſtant <hi>Ubi,</hi> for it was not come before it came: but from whence definitively, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from <hi>Heaven</hi> or <hi>Hell,</hi> we leave it to the <hi>Calviniſts.</hi> The <hi>Quò</hi> or <hi>Term</hi> of its coming was the <hi>Grave,</hi> he ſubſiſted there; but the <hi>end</hi> of the <hi>Comer,</hi> was the <hi>Re-union</hi> to the body, to make his real preſence there: but whether thereby he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came <hi>omnipreſent,</hi> to be eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where while he was in the <hi>grave,</hi> we leave to the <hi>Luther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi> His final intent, not to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganize
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170539:34"/>the body, it was not diſmembred, nor any way corrupted, not ſo much as <hi>in fieri,</hi> no not diſpoſitively, but to animate thoſe mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and to raiſe the body from the grave, in which action both the body and the ſoul had their mutual ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency, each co-elevating other to make up the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection:</hi> but whether theſe two Agents imply ſeveral o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perations really diſtinct, we leave it to the <hi>Nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lists.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The manner of his reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection ſo miraculous and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effable, that bad words ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs it beſt. In a moral rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the <hi>Jewes,</hi> it is here
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:170539:34"/>termed ſtealing: not to ſhew what our <hi>Saviour</hi> did in his riſing, but to intimate what the <hi>Jews</hi> had committed by their <hi>crucifying.</hi> Things of a ſuper-eminent nature are fain to borrow words of an inferiour ſignification, when they are related to a low ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity; ſo <hi>God</hi> gives him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf attributes, not as he is, but according to the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe whereby man appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends him. And here the action of our <hi>Saviour</hi> is ſet down, not as it is done, but according to the wickedneſs that the <hi>Jews</hi> had done. The active ſignification of ſtealing belongs to our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour,</hi> but the moral evil of it reflected upon others.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170539:35"/>The <hi>Law</hi> ſaith, he ſteals who fraudulently takes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ſomething of anothers, with intent to get the thing it ſelf, its uſe or poſſeſſion; if this definition be true, his reſurrection was ſtealing. His body was now <hi>cadaver puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti,</hi> the carcaſe of one that had publickly ſuffered, and thereby forfeit to the <hi>State;</hi> no man might meddle with it further then to bury it, nor that without ſpecial per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion; it was now none of his, his right and poſſeſſion of it both gone; <hi>tradiderat,</hi> he had made delivery of it, diſpenſed and paſſed it away to <hi>Pilat: Pilat</hi> diſpoſed his right to bury it, to the <hi>Watch</hi> to detain it, and now
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170539:35"/>it was theirs. When there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he took it from the <hi>Grave,</hi> he ſtole it: his <hi>repoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſsion</hi> of it defrauded all the <hi>Prae-detainers.</hi> Said they not alſo he was a Deceiver? But whether the Angel that rolled away the ſtone, were neceſſary or miniſterial, we leave it to the <hi>Hermoniſts.</hi> By natural <hi>relation</hi> his body was his <hi>own,</hi> as being the eſſential and proper coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-part of his ſoul, prae co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exiſtent with it in one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; but morally it was not ſo, or if it were, yet he might ſteal it for all that. A man may ſteal that which is his own, by interverting that right in it which hath been transferred to another: and
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170539:36"/>what kind of <hi>Theft</hi> this was, we leave it to the <hi>Lawyers.</hi> God forbid we ſhould lay other <hi>Theft</hi> to our <hi>Saviour,</hi> then that he attributes to himſelf, in ſaying, <hi>He came like a Thief in the night, (i. e.)</hi> ſecretly and una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares: ſo was his convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance from the <hi>Grave,</hi> cloſe, without the conſent and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of thoſe that were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; ſuch a carriage we commonly call ſtealth. We ſteal away from a room, when we depart without the knowledge of the <hi>Company:</hi> But whether he could con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey himſelf ſo cloſely, as to paſſe thorough the <hi>Tombe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone,</hi> we leave it to the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:170539:36"/>
            <p>Yet ſo cloſe it was, that the <hi>Watch</hi> perceived it not, for they were aſleep; they were ſet to watch it, but they did not. Not to watch is all one with not to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake, and that with to be be aſleep. We commonly call him ſleepy that is neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent or careleſs of what paſſeth, as the contrary we terme vigilant: ſo the <hi>Watch</hi> was faſt aſleep, they never gave heed to the <hi>Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> that ſo farre from their belief, that they had no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of it. But if death be a kind of ſleep, he is ſoundly aſleep that lies for dead, and ſo did the Watch, in the 4th verſe of this Chapter, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, for fear
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170539:37"/>of the <hi>Angel</hi> they fell a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and became as dead men. His preſence gave them a ſtrong <hi>Dormative,</hi> it wrought beyond ſleep. Sleep reacheth but only to a Ligation of ſenſe; but in them all motion ceaſed, they were examinate: but whether that fit held them onely by way of <hi>Syncope,</hi> or did determine in a <hi>Catapho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra,</hi> or <hi>ſoporiferous</hi> paſſion, we leave it to the <hi>Phyſitians. Fearful and Cowardiſh Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, more womaniſh than wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men!</hi> At the preſence of the <hi>Angel</hi> the <hi>Women</hi> ſtand upright, but the <hi>Souldiers</hi> fall in a ſwoun. Help them good <hi>Women,</hi> unbutton the <hi>Souldiers,</hi> ye need not fear
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170539:37"/>their <hi>Halberts.</hi> There's work for you and your <hi>Spices,</hi> your odours to comfort and recall their <hi>Spirits.</hi> Beſtow that <hi>Charity</hi> on the dying <hi>Souldiers</hi> which you inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on your dear <hi>Saviour;</hi> for he is riſen, and needs them not, but they may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit the <hi>Souldiers.</hi> The <hi>Souldiers</hi> uſed to ſuch fits, they had one of them the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther night in <hi>Gethſemane;</hi> but whether theſe dejections were ſins in the <hi>Souldiers,</hi> we leave to the <hi>Caſuiſts.</hi> Thus they were <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, laid as men aſleep; for it ſignifies rather the reclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or poſture of one aſleep, then the affection of ſleep it ſelf. He that lies ſtill
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170539:38"/>without ſenſe or motion, whether he be in a ſleep, or trance, or dead, we ſay <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and we call the <hi>Church-yard</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the dead lie there as if they were aſleep, they ſtir not. And ſo we muſt all be layd: There's no <hi>Dormitory.</hi> Our caſe ſomewhat like the <hi>Souldiers:</hi> We are appointed here to watch our <hi>Saviour;</hi> and as we do it, we are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the <hi>Souldiers</hi> infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, apt to be caſt aſleep, and become as dead men. Yet let us not be ſubject to their fear, our death is but like their ſwouning, that's the worſt. We are liable to riſe again, and our <hi>Reſurrection</hi> ſhall be like our <hi>Saviours:</hi>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:170539:38"/>His and ours make a mutual <hi>Aſpect;</hi> His the <hi>Specimen,</hi> and ours the <hi>Complement.</hi> What he practiſed on him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf he perfects in us: He will come again by night, and ſteal us to glory, while we lie ſleeping in the Grave. <hi>Even ſo come Lord Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:170539:39"/>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:170539:39"/>
            <head>THE RECANTATION SERMON.</head>
            <div type="preface">
               <head>The <hi>PREFACE</hi> before the <hi>SERMON.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Erſonall Prefaces are commonly unpleaſant, mine is to me: It is <hi>nomine poenae,</hi> it requires my <hi>patience,</hi> it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treats <hi>yours.</hi> I never came here <hi>ſponte,</hi> ſometimes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>requeſt,</hi> but now upon
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170539:40"/>
                  <hi>Command:</hi> to which my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience is very voluntary, as willing to give ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as any to receive it. I never ſtood here to ſhew my ſelf but now, and now not for worth, or wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but yet for weakneſs, in not diſcerning the three vitall circumſtances of a well ordered Action, <hi>Perſon, Time</hi> and <hi>Place.</hi> For it I am now Priſoner to <hi>cenſure,</hi> the Spectacle of <hi>ſubmiſsion,</hi> and Petitioner for <hi>pardon.</hi> It is good to be humble, I like it very well, and uſe it more then ſome men think I do. My preſent buſineſs is not to repeat that Sermon which the Repeater con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, and left unrepeated
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:170539:40"/>in the forenoon. I call it that, for now it is none of mine: It hath been cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red publickly and juſtly; and ſo let it ſuffer, the whole for ſome bad parts: as uſually the pravity of one member is deſtructive to the whole body. If ye will pleaſe to let it die, I will ſubſtitute another in the room; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to (though enjoyned by Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority) my ſelf doth moſt willingly condeſcend. My Text was alſo impoſed, and delivered in theſe words, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. In proſecution whereof, I humbly crave a fair con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and a favourable acceptation. Firſt, for my offence paſt, that my <hi>readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:170539:41"/>to acknowledge it may go for one degree of <hi>ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction,</hi> and <hi>ſudden recantati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> for another. What it wants in ripeneſs is ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in ſincerity, though in this the more mature, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the more timely. Secondly, for my preſent memory, I have had no time to furniſh it: it is a dull and drowſie faculty, a great deal of do to make it ready; and beſides, it is ſomewhat cowardly in point of danger. It dares not ſhew it ſelf, the leaſt agitation makes it run away; and my ſelf hath partly ſpared it for your ſake and the Univerſity. My preſent Sermon is but a Brief, I would deſire you
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170539:41"/>to hear it read. You may pleaſe to turn to the Text; Its written
<q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Acts</hi> 2.1. the latter part,</bibl>
                     <p>They were all with one ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord in one place.</p>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="sermon">
               <p>
                  <hi>Man</hi> ceaſeth to be <hi>Man,</hi> if we conceive him <hi>all-ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient; God</hi> onely is ſo, He onely is <hi>all-ſufficient</hi> who is onely <hi>Almighty.</hi> Mans being and his good is indigency and want: his chiefeſt buſineſs is to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend againſt it, and his hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs to aboliſh it. <hi>Private want</hi> is an occaſion of <hi>diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> and <hi>diſſent;</hi> but <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon want</hi> the common cauſe of <hi>Concord,</hi> the <hi>Parent</hi> and <hi>procurer</hi> of moral unity
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:170539:42"/>and all humane ſocieties. So all our Aſſemblies are grounded upon want, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to give thanks that the paſt hath been ſupplied, but commonly to ſupply the wants preſent. The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, that when a Plurality of Agents are united in their efficacy, the operation is farre more effectual then if each wrought ſingle: and what the ſingle members cannot obtain apart, they may acquire joyntly, being incorporate into one body. This alſo is the caſe of Chriſts Diſciples, the want of their Maſter collects and imbodies them in together. They want him twice, once on Mount <hi>Calvary;</hi> there
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170539:42"/>they want his ſoul; this ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers them cloſe in <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem;</hi> and the door is ſhut on them, but the place not ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified.</p>
               <p>The ſecond time he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſakes them on Mount <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet,</hi> at the 9th verſe of the former Chapter, then they want his perſon: that puts them together again at the 13th verſe, in the upper room; there they conſider of another want, meanes to perform their Miniſtry. <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> the Traitor hath hang'd himſelf, at the 18th verſe, his Biſhoprick is voyd, and they will chooſe another in his room, at the 22th verſe; there they prick two, then
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:170539:43"/>pray and draw lots; and at the laſt verſe <hi>Matthias</hi> is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected and conſecrated. All this being finiſhed, they yet find another want, variety of Languages to utter their Embaſſie to ſeveral Nations, where they were to be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed. For this there is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other meeting upon a ſet day, the fifth from the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, and the tenth from the Aſcenſion; and then, as it is in my Text, <hi>They were all with one accord in one place.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In which may it pleaſe you to obſerve three Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances;</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. The plurality or num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber;
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:170539:43"/>
                     <hi>they were all.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. Their unanimity or morall union of ſoul; <hi>with one accord.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. The unipreſence, or locall union of body; <hi>In one place.</hi> Of theſe in their order, as the time hath ſcanted, and God ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by weakned thoughts. We begin with the Plurali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or number; <hi>They were all.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>The Expoſitors run much <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con,</hi> about the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of theſe <hi>all,</hi> whether therein the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> and other Women were inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: But for the moſt, they
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:170539:44"/>go by conjecture, and ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther affirm, or deny it to ſerve their own purpoſe; and ſeeing the Scripture declares neither, we may exclude them to ſerve ours. They might be in preſence, but not as part of the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, and partakers of the benefits. The reaſon of this conjecture is, though the Women otherwiſe might receive many gifts and graces, yet they were not fit veſſels to be filled with the holy Ghoſt in this kind, to ſpeak with divers tongues. The ſub-reaſon is, they might not exerciſe the functions for which theſe Tongues were ordained; they were for <hi>prophecying in
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:170539:44"/>the Church,</hi> from which St. <hi>Paul</hi> debarres the Women, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.24. <hi>Let your Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men keep ſilence in the Church, for it is not permitted unto them to ſpeak.</hi> Let us not be thought over-weening for caſting now and then a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture diverſe from the common current. We are <hi>free Deniſons</hi> of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> and may challenge the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of our <hi>thoughts</hi> as well as <hi>out-landiſh men.</hi> Let their learning not out-look us, for where the Scripture leaves us, all learning lies lame, and her two truths are <hi>Criticiſmes</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectures.</hi> What perſons ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver excluded, the Diſciples
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:170539:45"/>will not: they are ordered in this <hi>(all;)</hi> for the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtory-Cardinalls will be in no order; for they make the Canons hold, that the Clauſe, <hi>All manner of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> doth not include a Cardinall.</p>
               <p>The number is univerſal; not collective, but repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative for the whole primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church, who was <hi>all</hi> there, not in their own ſingle, but in the perſons of theſe <hi>(all:)</hi> who were there for the acceptation of the holy Ghoſt, according to the gracious promiſes of our Saviour; or haply, all relatively too, the number ſpecified in the Aſſembly
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:170539:45"/>for the election of <hi>Matthias.</hi> The total ſum of that <hi>all</hi> was about 120. at the 15. verſe of the former Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: the major part was the 12. Apoſtles. 12. the major part of 120. not in <hi>number,</hi> but in <hi>power,</hi> and therefore the better part; though ſome think otherwiſe, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon infer, that every ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary man is as good as a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop. The number here is 12. not unſignificant: the 12. Diſciples anſwering the 12. Patriarchs; for ſo it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God, that both the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaments, the new and old, ſhould be founded upon <hi>dodecadies;</hi> as the Church of the Jews under the Law
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:170539:46"/>ſprung from the twelve <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs,</hi> ſo the Church of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> under the Goſpel from the twelve <hi>Apostles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Fathers and after-Divines, both ancient and modern, do much deſcant upon the number of the 12. Apoſtles, in relation to the 12. Fountains in <hi>Elim,</hi> and 12. Stones in <hi>Aarons</hi> breaſt-plate, the 12. Stones of the Altar, the 12. loaves of Propoſition, the 12. Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites that carried the Ark, the 12. ſpies ſent to ſearch the Land of promiſe, the 12. gates of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the 12. Signes of the <hi>Zodiack,</hi> moneths of the year, and hours of the day, with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:170539:46"/>more the like; ſome whereof are pious, others but fancies. Yet in each they frame out a reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance, as ye may ſee at large in <hi>Palmeron,</hi> and divers others. With the twelve A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles the reſt of the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples made up one hundred and twenty.</p>
               <p>Hereon St. <hi>Auſtine</hi> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralls in his one hundred and ſixteenth Sermon <hi>de Temp.</hi> that the holy Ghoſt was given ten-fold to the twelve Apoſtles, becauſe that ten multipiled by twelve makes up the product one hundred and twenty. But the morall of St. <hi>Gregory</hi> in his 35. Moral, and 3d Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:170539:47"/>is too myſtical, if not meerly <hi>Pythagorical:</hi> he would have 120. partly to ſignifie things temporall, partly eternal, by this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction; an hundred and twenty by Arithmeticall progreſſe ariſeth from one to fifteen; and becauſe the components are ſeven and eight, things temporal are conceived by ſeven, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall by eight: of this I conceive not the ground, nor find it approved in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rithmetick. If thus to break numbers were rational, a man might deduce 600. my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries from the number 120. St. <hi>Jerome</hi> prefigures this number in the age of
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:170539:47"/>
                  <hi>Moſes,</hi> whoſe years were full one hundred and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. With modeſty be it ſpoken, St. <hi>Jerome</hi> might have pretyped it by the age of man in general, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.3. when God ſaith of man, that his <hi>years ſhall be one hundred and twenty.</hi> Then put <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and <hi>Man</hi> together, and the réſemblance will be ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall: <hi>Moſes</hi> a type of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the Scriptures both ſay and ſhew it.</p>
               <p>As the Law deſcended firſt from God upon <hi>Moſes</hi> alone, and after him to the people; ſo the deſcent of the holy Ghoſt, firſt from God upon Chriſt alone, and after from Chriſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all the Diſciples, whoſe
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:170539:48"/>utmoſt number was about one hundred and twenty men, and from them com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated to the utmoſt of mankind, whoſe utmoſt age is but 120. years; but for the purpoſe, this mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber is more preciſely typed in 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 5.15. at the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end of the verſe, by one hundred and twenty Prieſts ſounding on Trumpets, whereas it came to paſſe that the Trumpeters and Singers were all one to make one ſound: ſo here the Diſciples, though 120. in number, yet but one accord; which is my ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond circumſtance, the una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity or moral union of ſoul; <hi>with one accord.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:170539:48"/>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: what the word means is ſhewed in the fourth Chapter follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, at the thirty ſecond verſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>They were of one heart and one ſoul;</hi> not Phyſically but Morally, an union and moral identity of ſouls, not the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive ſoul, underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or ſenſe. Accord con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts not in aſſent of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or points of ſpeculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for to him that affirms the Sun bigger then the earth, my aſſent or diſſent neither makes nor marres one accord: The reaſon is, for that the judgment in ſuch caſes proceeds from natural reaſon, and by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:170539:49"/>from neceſſity; but in accord it ſprings from the will, from a voluntary choice and free: for true accord is an union of the motive ſoul, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, an union of the Will and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections; not the faculties themſelves, though much at diſcord, but in unanimous actions and operations re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting from the faculties, when our <hi>Velle's</hi> and <hi>Nolle's</hi> are one and the ſame, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther concerning the end it ſelf, in the ſame fruition or intention, or concerning the means that led us to that end. In the ſumme, councel and conſent, they ſavour choice and
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:170539:49"/>uſe: and all this not in matters trivial, but things of moment, where there lies a ſenſible com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity to a good commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
               <p>Thus was the unanimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and accord of the Diſciples; firſt, for the end, they have <hi>one accord</hi> for the fruition of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, and intent to publiſh it; eſpecially the point of Reſurrection. Secondly, for the <hi>means; one ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord</hi> for counſel and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and <hi>one</hi> for choice and uſe of them. And yet their <hi>one accord</hi> ſtands not here, but deſcends <hi>ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cor:</hi>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:170539:50"/>it ſignifies a co-heartedneſs, an unanimity or concurrring in affection; <hi>one accord</hi> in love and hatred, in deſire and diſlike, in joy and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and ſo in other paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons iraſcible; yea there moſt of all, for where there lies a <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, there's moſt properly <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: where all theſe agree in one, ther's truly one accord. To this if we ſuperadde a quantity of <hi>Impetus,</hi> a vehemency to conquer all impediments or difficulties of the action, we hit juſt on the nature of the thing; for then we are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, when our agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is the ſame, and hath the ſame degrees in opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:170539:50"/>where we have a propenſe and earneſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence jointly to proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the ſame good, or ſhunne the ſame evil, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing either action the ſame way. And thus were the Diſciples in their affections <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the ſame love, deſire and joy concerning the publiſhing of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, and good news of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; and the ſame hate, diſlike and ſorrow for any evil that might oppoſe it. Their affections, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore were irregular, and caſt on infirmities, as Ambition, Incredulity, Apoſtaſie, were now rectified and directed to their right object. It
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:170539:51"/>was not any rude <hi>accord,</hi> where the worſt do rule; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was it a diſſembling <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord,</hi> with a league in the mouth, and diſcord at the heart; neither was it a wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>accord,</hi> as of the <hi>Epheſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> for their idolatry; but of <hi>good men</hi> with a <hi>good mind</hi> and to a <hi>good end.</hi> Thus were the Diſciples to receive the Holy Ghoſt. This <hi>accord</hi> had God to its efficient; for as God onely makes the heart, ſo he onely ſeaſons it, and gives it grace. It had God for its author, and God for its end, and therefore brings to <hi>one place;</hi> which is my third circumſtance.</p>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:170539:51"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the ſame place;</hi> Not the ſame place numerically, but relatively, in the ſame room. This place was a high place; it was an <hi>upper room</hi> and comely. We ſhould do all religious exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes in a decent place; the paring away of <hi>ceremonies</hi> do but take away the <hi>Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches ornaments.</hi> Then it was a <hi>high room:</hi> at all ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual exerciſes we ſhould aſcend. Now it is called in Latine <hi>Coenaculum,</hi> a room to ſupp in: All reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious exerciſes ſhould be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun with the <hi>Supper of the Lord;</hi> and that muſt be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon too, not for one only: this room (ſome ſay) was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:170539:52"/>to <hi>Nicodemus;</hi> yet this proves not for <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticles:</hi> for if we have the like authority, we will releaſe our Canon. What if we ſay, this is <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Porch? for there were ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore perſons, and it was noiſed about by and by, yea by nine of the clock <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> was in his Sermon: This therefore is like not to be in a private chamber: but were not this, yet the other was, <hi>verſe</hi> 46.</p>
               <p>God would have them joyn together to receive the Holy Ghoſt; for where the hearts are together it is much, but where they are
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:170539:52"/>together, and their body in one place, there is all the good place can afford. Thus we came from the plurali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the unanimity, and from the unanimity to the unipreſence; the firſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the ſecond is but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed, and the ſecond with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the third is but ſingula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; but theſe altogether make a complete Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>And now for application of what hath been ſaid to our Parliament; In the Diſciples a ſpiritual want was the cauſe of their aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, in the Parliament a temporal want. The
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:170539:53"/>event in the one was good; God grant it be ſo in the other. The time of that was after the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, and ſo is it of this. The perſons are all alike, <hi>Men</hi> all, no <hi>women,</hi> they are too talkative. The number alike, <hi>thoſe,</hi> all the <hi>Primitive Church; theſe,</hi> all the <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</hi> Of them both our opinions are alike; the one we honour, and the other too, a true Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>givers. They were una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous and unipreſent, and ſo alſo is the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; they had one Counſel, ſo have we; their <hi>accord</hi> was good,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:170539:53"/>and ſo is ours; perfect, to cut off all bad <hi>accord.</hi> Their <hi>accord</hi> reſolves a ſpiritual welfare, and ſo is our accord, to maintain our ſelves by warre. So of theſe our opinions are alike; the one would be without warre, were they not provoked thereto, but now 'tis needful: ſo is our warre alſo. That was an upper room, high and ſtately, ſo is the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament; that was in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbs of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> this of <hi>London.</hi> Now let us praiſe God for them, and pray for them, that there be not oppoſition between them. Let the <hi>King</hi> be
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:170539:54"/>the <hi>Head,</hi> they the <hi>Heart,</hi> we the <hi>Members.</hi> Let it be like the Parliament in <hi>Mount Sinai,</hi> the King and ſubjects as <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> and we like the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites.</hi> Let God ſay to the King, that he will <hi>help him,</hi> and <hi>deſtroy his enemies:</hi> Let the King ſay to the people as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> to the <hi>Gibeonites;</hi> and let the people ſay to him as <hi>Iſrael</hi> to <hi>David, We will ſerve and obey thee onely, and do what thou commandeſt us:</hi> and let me pray for them, that they may ſtand faſt in the Faith: and let's all ſay of them all that be
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:170539:54"/>of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as a Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of one minde, that this union may be ruled by order, and that like this ſpiritual one, let's pray there may be <hi>one God, one Minde, one Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit;</hi> and let all the people ſay, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here remains as yet a perſonal concluſion. If I heretofore ſeemed to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver any Doctrine contrary to this I now deliver, I ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly renounce it. The laſt time I had theſe words, <hi>Now the Peaſant thinks, &amp;c.</hi> I I had alſo theſe words, <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing contents the Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty but war and contention.</hi>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:170539:55"/>I there I did very ill, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting that of <hi>Solomon, There is a time for warre, and a time for peace.</hi> For another erroneous thing I require your pardon. A word once ſpoken cannot be recalled, it may be ſtopt. In the ſame place where the blot was made I am come to wipe it out. My laſt Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to you is for patronage from further trouble.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
